Thank you.
شُكراً لكم
It's a real pleasure to be here.
أنه لفخر لي أن اكون هنا
I last did a TED Talk
المرة الماضية التي قدمت فيها حديثاً لمؤتمر تيد
I think about seven years ago or so.
كانت منذ حوالي سبع سنوات او نحو ذلك
I talked about spaghetti sauce.
لقد تحدثت حينها عن صلصلة الاسبغتي
And so many people, I guess, watch those videos.
والعديد من الاشخاص شاهد ذلك الفيديو
People have been coming up to me ever since
وكان يأتي الناس إلي منذ ذاك الحين
to ask me questions about spaghetti sauce,
لكي يطرحوا علي أسئلة متعلقة بصلصلة الإسبغتي
which is a wonderful thing in the short term --
وهو أمرٌ ممتع على المدى القصير
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
but it's proven to be less than ideal
ولكنه و قد تبين لي أنها ليست حالة مثالية
over seven years.
على مدى السنوات السبع
And so I though I would come
لذا قلت يجب أن أأتي
and try and put spaghetti sauce behind me.
واحاول التحدث عن أمر يضع قصة صلصلة الإسباغتي في طي النسيان
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The theme of this morning's session is Things We Make.
ان عنوان هذه الفقرة من المؤتمر هو " الاشياء التي نخترع "
And so I thought I would tell a story
فخطر لي أن أقص قصة
about someone
عن شخص
who made one of the most precious objects
صنع شيء ذا اهمية كبيرة جداً
of his era.
في عصره
And the man's name is Carl Norden.
وأسمه
Carl Norden was born in 1880.
كارل نوردن و قد ولد في 1880
And he was Swiss.
وكان سويسري الجنسية
And of course, the Swiss can be divided
و السويسريون يمكن تقسيمهم
into two general categories:
الى فئتين
those who make small, exquisite,
فئة تصنع المنتجات الصغيرة الراقية المبدعة
expensive objects
الباهظة الثمن
and those who handle the money
وفئة تدير أموال الاشخاص
of those who buy small, exquisite,
الذين يشترون المنتجات الصغيرة الراقية المبدعة
expensive objects.
باهظة الثمن
And Carl Norden is very firmly in the former camp.
و كارل نوردن كان من الفئة الاولى
He's an engineer.
هو مهندس
He goes to the Federal Polytech in Zurich.
لقد درس في زيورخ في جامعة بولي التكنولوجية
In fact, one of his classmates is a young man named Lenin
في الحقيقة كان احد زملائه يدعى " لينن "
who would go on
والذي سوف يستمر في حياته
to break small, expensive, exquisite objects.
يدمر الاشياء الصغيرة الباهظة
And he's a Swiss engineer, Carl.
وقد كان كارل مهندساً سويسرياً
And I mean that in its fullest sense of the word.
واعني بهذا كل ما تحمله الكلمة من معنى
He wears three-piece suits;
لقد كان يرتدي حلة من ثلاثة قطع
and he has a very, very small, important mustache;
وكان لديه شارب صغير جداً عزيز عليه
and he is domineering
وقد كان متسلطاً
and narcissistic
ونرجسياً
and driven
و مندفعاً
and has an extraordinary ego;
وكان لديه غرور متقدٌ كبير جداً
and he works 16-hour days;
وكان يعمل 16 ساعة في اليوم
and he has very strong feelings about alternating current;
وكان لديه شعور قوي بوجوب السير عكس التيار السائد
and he feels like a suntan is a sign of moral weakness;
وكان يشعر ان سمرته عبارة عن دليل عن ضعفه الاخلاقي
and he drinks lots of coffee;
وكان يشرب الكثير من القهوة
and he does his best work
وكان الأفضل في عمله
sitting in his mother's kitchen in Zurich for hours
وكان يقبع في مطبخ والدته في زيورخ لساعات
in complete silence
دون أن ينبس بأي همسة
with nothing but a slide rule.
ودون أن يعبث بشيء سوى بمسطرته
In any case,
خلاصةً
Carl Norden emigrates to the United States
لقد هاجر لاحقاً الى الولايات المتحدة الامريكية
just before the First World War
قبل الحرب العالمية الاولى
and sets up shop on Lafayette Street
وافتتح محلاً في شارع لافييت
in downtown Manhattan.
في منتصف مدينة مانهاتن
And he becomes obsessed with the question
وقد بات مهوساً بالسؤال
of how to drop bombs from an airplane.
عن كيفية إلقاء القنابل من الطائرات
Now if you think about it,
والآن إن فكرتم بها
in the age before GPS and radar,
ففي عصر ما قبل الجي بي إس
that was obviously a really difficult problem.
كانت تلك معضلة كبيرة
It's a complicated physics problem.
كان معضلة فيزيائية كبيرة
You've got a plane that's thousands of feet up in the air,
فالطائرة تحلق على ارتفاع عدة آلاف من الاقدام عن سطح الارض
going at hundreds of miles an hour,
وتحلق بسرعة مئات الاميال في الساعة
and you're trying to drop an object, a bomb,
ويتوجب عليها ان تلقي قنبلة
towards some stationary target
اتجاه موقع الهدف
in the face of all kinds of winds and cloud cover
بالاخذ بعين الاعتبار كل الرياح والسحب التي تغطي و تعترض الهدف
and all kinds of other impediments.
وكل المعطيات و المعوقات الأخرى
And all sorts of people,
ان جميع الاطياف العسكرية
moving up to the First World War and between the wars,
منذ الحرب العالمية الاولى و حتى الثانية
tried to solve this problem,
حاولوا حل هذه المعضلة
and nearly everybody came up short.
ولم يستطع احد ان يصل اليه
The bombsights that were available
فقد كانت موجهات القنابل الموجودة حينها
were incredibly crude.
فاشلةٌ تماماً
But Carl Norden is really the one who cracks the code.
ولكن كارل نوردن استطاع حقاً ان يفك معضلة تلك المشكلة
And he comes up with this incredibly complicated device.
واستطاع ان يخترج جهاز مميزاً معقداً
It weighs about 50 lbs.
يزن ما يقارب 50 رطل
It's called the Norden Mark 15 bombsight.
يدعى موجه نوردن مارك 15 للقنابل
And it has all kinds of levers and ball-bearings
ويضم العديد من أنواع الروافع والمحامل
and gadgets and gauges.
والأدوات وأجهزة القياس.
And he makes this complicated thing.
لتكون جهازاً معقداً
And what he allows people to do
وما قام به كارل
is he makes the bombardier take this particular object,
هو انه عمد الى توكيل مهمة الى العسكري موجه القنابل بان يستخدم الجهاز
visually sight the target,
بعد ان يحصل على رؤية مرئية للهدف
because they're in the Plexiglas cone of the bomber,
من خلال كوة توجيه و وتخزين القنابل
and then they plug in the altitude of the plane,
ومن ثم يقوم العسكري بادخال ارتفاع الطائرة
the speed of the plane, the speed of the wind
وسرعتها وسرعة الرياح
and the coordinates
والاحداثيات المطلوبة
of the target.
للهدف
And the bombsight will tell him when to drop the bomb.
وسوف يخبره الجهاز حينها عن موعد القاء القنابل
And as Norden famously says,
وكما كان يقول نوردن عبارته الشهيرة
"Before that bombsight came along,
" قبل أن اخترع موجه القنابل
bombs would routinely miss their target
كانت القنابل تسقط بعيداً عن اهدافها بصورة دائمة
by a mile or more."
بميل أو أكثر "
But he said, with the Mark 15 Norden bombsight,
ولكنه قال انه وباستخدام موجه "نوردن " للقنابل مارك 15
he could drop a bomb into a pickle barrel
يمكن القاء قنبلة في برميل لحفظ المخللات
at 20,000 ft.
من إرتفاع 20 ألف قدم
Now I cannot tell you
لا يمكنني أن اخبركم
how incredibly excited
كم كان الجيش الامريكي
the U.S. military was
متحمس لهذا الخبر
by the news of the Norden bombsight.
عن موجه "نوردن " للقنابل
It was like manna from heaven.
لقد كانت هبة من الجنة
Here was an army
فقد كان لدينا جيش
that had just had experience in the First World War,
لديه تجربة في الحرب العالمية الاولى
where millions of men
حيث ملايين الرجال
fought each other in the trenches,
حاربوا في الخنادق
getting nowhere, making no progress,
وقتل الآلاف منهم دون اي تقدم عسكري مقنع
and here someone had come up with a device
وما حدث ان جاء كارل و اخترع جهازاً
that allowed them to fly up in the skies
يمكنهم من الاقلاع في أعالي السماء
high above enemy territory
فوق منطقة العدو
and destroy whatever they wanted
وتدمير ما يحلو لهم
with pinpoint accuracy.
بدقة متناهية
And the U.S. military
وقام الجيش الامريكي
spends 1.5 billion dollars --
بصرف ما يقارب مليار ونصف دولار
billion dollars in 1940 dollars --
من دولارات عام 1940
developing the Norden bombsight.
لكي يتم تطوير موجه "نوردن " للقنابل
And to put that in perspective,
ولكي تستوعبون الصورة جيداً
the total cost of the Manhattan project
فان مشروع منهاتن
was three billion dollars.
كلف حينها 3 مليارات دولار
Half as much money was spent on this Norden bombsight
اي ما دفع لأجل مشروع موجه "نوردن " للقنابل يعادل نصف
as was spent on the most famous military-industrial project
مادفع على اشهر مشروع عسكري صناعي
of the modern era.
في الحقبة الحديثة
And there were people, strategists, within the U.S. military
ولقد كان هناك استراتيجيون في الجيش الامريكي
who genuinely thought that this single device
يظنون ان هذا الجهاز بحد ذاته
was going to spell the difference
سوف يقلب موازين الحرب
between defeat and victory
من الهزيمة الى النصر
when it came to the battle against the Nazis
عندما يواجهون النازيون
and against the Japanese.
او اليابانيون
And for Norden as well,
و الامر كان لنوردن
this device had incredible moral importance,
ان هذا الجهاز موجه القنابل له بعد اخلاقي
because Norden was a committed Christian.
لان نوردن كان مسيحيٌ ملتزم
In fact, he would always get upset
في الحقيقة كان يمتعض
when people referred to the bombsight as his invention,
عندما كان الناس يشيرون الى موجه القنابل على انه اختراعه الشخصي
because in his eyes,
اذ كان يرى الموضوع من وجهة نظر اخرى
only God could invent things.
حيث من وجهة نظره ان الله من يملك العلم
He was simply the instrument of God's will.
وهو مجرد وسيلة لتحقيق ذلك
And what was God's will?
وما هي مشيئة الله بنظره بخصوص هذا ؟
Well God's will was that the amount of suffering in any kind of war
حسناً كان يقول انه بواسطة هذا الاختراع كان سيقلل من
be reduced to as small an amount as possible.
الخسائر التي تنتج عن الحروب بأكثر قدر ممكن
And what did the Norden bombsight do?
وما كان هدف موجه "نوردن " للقنابل ؟
Well it allowed you to do that.
هو تمكين ذلك من الحدوث - تقليل الخسائر -
It allowed you to bomb only those things
انه يسمح لك بإلقاء القنابل فقط على الاهداف العسكرية
that you absolutely needed and wanted to bomb.
والتي تحتاج فقط لقصفها
So in the years leading up to the Second World War,
لذا في السنوات التي سبقت الحرب العالمية الثانية
the U.S. military buys 90,000
اشترى الجيش الامريكي 90 ألأف من
of these Norden bombsights
موجه "نوردن " للقنابل
at a cost of $14,000 each --
حيث كان يكلف الجهاز الواحد منها 14 ألف دولار
again, in 1940 dollars, that's a lot of money.
ومرة أخرى اذكر كان هذا عام 1940 أي الكثير من المال
And they trained 50,000 bombardiers on how to use them --
وقد درب الجيش 50 ألف عسكري للعمل على الجهاز
long extensive, months-long training sessions --
ضمن برنامج تدريبي طويل مكثف
because these things are essentially analog computers;
لان هذا الجهاز كان يحتاج التعامل مع الحاسوب
they're not easy to use.
والذي لم يكن حينها استخدامه سهل
And they make every one of those bombardiers take an oath,
وقد تم فرض قسم على جميع العسكرين موجهي القنابل
to swear that if they're ever captured,
بأن يقسموا بأنه لو تم إلقاء القبض عليهم
they will not divulge a single detail
بأن لا يفصحوا بأي معلومة بخصوصه
of this particular device to the enemy,
للعدو وان لا يفضوا اي تفصيل عن ذلك الجهاز
because it's imperative the enemy not get their hands
لانه من المحوري جداً ان يضع العدو يده على هذا الجهاز
on this absolutely essential piece of technology.
لانه كان حصيلة تكنولوجية أساسية هامة
And whenever the Norden bombsight is taken onto a plane,
وعندما كان موجه "نوردن " للقنابل يؤخذ لكي يوضع في الطائرات
it's escorted there by a series of armed guards.
كان يتم مرافقة الجهاز بعدة حراس مسلحون
And it's carried in a box with a canvas shroud over it.
وكان يوضع في علبة مغطاة جيداً بقماش
And the box is handcuffed to one of the guards.
وكان الجهاز موصداً بمعصم أحد الحراس
It's never allowed to be photographed.
ولم يكن يسمح على الاطلاق التصوير
And there's a little incendiary device inside of it,
وكان فيه جهاز في داخل الموجه
so that, if the plane ever crashes, it will be destroyed
يعمل على تدمير الجهاز في حال سقوط الطائرة
and there's no way the enemy can ever get their hands on it.
لذا لم يكن هناك من اي وسيلة للعدو من ان يضع يده عليه
The Norden bombsight
إن موجه "نوردن " للقنابل
is the Holy Grail.
كان يمثل " الكأس المقدسة "
So what happens during the Second World War?
إذا ماذا حدث في الحرب العالمية الثانية ؟
Well, it turns out it's not the Holy Grail.
لقد تبين ان الجهاز ليس الكأس المقدسة
In practice, the Norden bombsight
اثناء استخدامه .. فموجه نوردن للقنابل
can drop a bomb into a pickle barrel at 20,000 ft.,
يستطيع اصابة برميل مخلل من على ارتفاع 20 الف قدم
but that's under perfect conditions.
ولكن هذا في الظروف المثالية
And of course, in wartime,
ولكن في الواقع و اثناء الحرب
conditions aren't perfect.
لم تكن الظروف مثالية على الاطلاق
First of all, it's really hard to use -- really hard to use.
فبداية كان من الصعوبة بمكان استخدامه بإتقان
And not all of the people
فلم يستطع الجميع
who are of those 50,000 men who are bombardiers
من الجنود الذين تدربوا والذين كانوا 50 ألفاً كموجهي قنابل
have the ability to properly program an analog computer.
ان يتعاملوا مع برنامج الحاسوب
Secondly, it breaks down a lot.
كما كان الجهاز يصاب بالعطب كثيراً
It's full of all kinds of gyroscopes and pulleys
فكل تلك الجيروسكوبات والبكرات
and gadgets and ball-bearings,
والأدوات والكرات
and they don't work as well as they ought to
لم تكن تعمل كما يجب
in the heat of battle.
في خضم المعركة
Thirdly, when Norden was making his calculations,
ثالثاً عندما كان يُعد نورد حساباته للجهاز
he assumed that a plane would be flying
افترض ان الطائرة سوف تحلق
at a relatively slow speed at low altitudes.
بسرعة منخفضة نسبياً و على ارتفاع منخفض
Well in a real war, you can't do that;
ولكن في الحرب الحقيقة لا يمكنك القيام بذلك
you'll get shot down.
فذلك سيمكن الاعداء من اسقاط الطائرة
So they started flying them at high altitudes at incredibly high speeds.
وما حدث هو أن الطائرات باتت تحلق على ارتفاعات عالية وبسرعات كبيرة
And the Norden bombsight doesn't work as well
ولم يعمل موجه "نوردن " للقنابل جيداً
under those conditions.
تحت تلك الظروف
But most of all,
ولكن النقطة الاهم
the Norden bombsight required the bombardier
هو ان العسكري الذي يعمل على موجه "نوردن " للقنابل
to make visual contact with the target.
يتوجب عليه أن يحصل على رؤية بصرية للهدف
But of course, what happens in real life?
ولكن في الحقيقة .. ما الذي يحدث في الحياة الواقعية ؟
There are clouds, right.
هناك حتماً السحب
It needs cloudless sky to be really accurate.
فانت تحتاج سماء صافية من اجل دقة عالية
Well how many cloudless skies
حسناً كم من السماوات الصافية
do you think there were above Central Europe
يمكن أن توجد في منتصف أوروبا
between 1940 and 1945?
بين عام 1940 و 1945
Not a lot.
ليس الكثير حتماً
And then to give you a sense
ولكي أعطيكم صورة عن
of just how inaccurate the Norden bombsight was,
مقدار الدقة لموجه "نوردن " للقنابل أثناء الحرب
there was a famous case in 1944
كان هناك موقعة في عام 1944
where the Allies bombed a chemical plant in Leuna, Germany.
عندما كان يريد الحلفاء قصف مصنع للمواد الكيميائية في لينوا ألمانيا
And the chemical plant comprised
وكان المصنع الكيميائي
757 acres.
يمتد على 757 فدان
And over the course of 22 bombing missions,
وعلى مدى ال 22 مهمة قصف
the Allies dropped 85,000 bombs
التي تم رمي 85 ألف قنبلة فيها من قبل الحلفاء
on this 757 acre chemical plant,
على معمل الكيميائيات ذا ال757 فدان
using the Norden bombsight.
بإستخدام موجه "نوردن " للقنابل
Well what percentage of those bombs
كانت النسبة المئوية لإصابة الهدف حينها
do you think actually landed
التي استطاعت فيها القنابل حقاً
inside the 700-acre perimeter of the plant?
السقوط داخل محيط المصنع الذي يبلغ 700 فدان
10 percent. 10 percent.
هي 10 % فقط 10%
And of those 10 percent that landed,
ومن تلك القنابل ال10 %
16 percent didn't even go off; they were duds.
16% منها لم تنفجر .. فقد كانت معطوبة
The Leuna chemical plant,
و مصنع لينوا الكيميائي
after one of the most extensive bombings in the history of the war,
بعد اكبر قصف مركز حدث في تاريخ الحرب العالمية الثانية
was up and running within weeks.
استطاع خلال اسابيع ان يعاود العمل
And by the way, all those precautions
وبالمناسبة كل تلك الاحتياطات لكي
to keep the Norden bombsight out of the hands of the Nazis?
يبقى موجه "نوردن " للقنابل بعيداً عن أيدي النازيين
Well it turns out
تبين أنها بلا جدوى
that Carl Norden, as a proper Swiss,
لان كارل نوردن كسويسري اعتيادي
was very enamored of German engineers.
كان محاطاً بالعديد من المهندسين الألمان
So in the 1930s, he hired a whole bunch of them,
ففي عام 1930 وظف عدة منهم
including a man named Hermann Long
كان من بينهم رجل يدعى هرمن لونج
who, in 1938,
والذي في عام 1938
gave a complete set of the plans for the Norden bombsight to the Nazis.
اعطى نسخة كاملة من تصاميم موجه "نوردن " للقنابل للنازيين
So they had their own Norden bombsight throughout the entire war --
لذا كان لدى النازيين نسخة خاصة بهم من موجه "نوردن " للقنابل
which also, by the way, didn't work very well.
الذي لم يعمل جيداً أيضاً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So why do we talk about the Norden bombsight?
حسناً لماذا أحدثكم إذاً عن موجه "نوردن " للقنابل
Well because we live in an age
لاننا في الحقيقة نعيش في عصر
where there are lots and lots
فيه الكثير والكثير من أمثال جهاز
of Norden bombsights.
موجه "نوردن " للقنابل
We live in a time where there are all kinds
نحن نعيش في عصر في العديد من انواع
of really, really smart people
البشر الاذكياء حقاً
running around, saying that they've invented gadgets
الذين يجوبون العالم و هم يقولون أنهم أخترعوا الاختراعات
that will forever change our world.
التي سوف تغير العالم للأبد
They've invented websites that will allow people to be free.
فمنهم من اخترع موقعاً الكترونياً يسمح للناس بأن يكونوا احراراً
They've invented some kind of this thing, or this thing, or this thing
ومنهم من اخترعوا كذا و كذا
that will make our world forever better.
والذي سوف يحيل عالمنا للأبد نحو الافضل
If you go into the military,
ان نظرتم الى الجيش
you'll find lots of Carl Nordens as well.
سوف ترون الكثير من امثال " كارل نوردن "
If you go to the Pentagon, they will say,
وان ذهبتم الى البنتاجون سوف يقولون لكم
"You know what, now we really can
أتعلمون نحن نستطيع اليوم حقاً
put a bomb inside a pickle barrel
ان نسقط قنبلة في برميل مخلل
at 20,000 ft."
من ارتفاع 20 ألف قدم
And you know what, it's true; they actually can do that now.
أتعلمون .. انها حقيقة انهم يستطيعون ذلك الآن
But we need to be very clear
ولكن علينا ان نكون واضحين تماما
about how little that means.
عن ماهية ذلك الامر
In the Iraq War, at the beginning of the first Iraq War,
في حرب العراق الأولى .. في بداية حرب العراق
the U.S. military, the air force,
الجيش الامريكي , سلاح الجو تحديداً
sent two squadrons of F-15E Fighter Eagles
أرسل سربين من النسور المقاتلة من طراز F - 15E
to the Iraqi desert
الى الصحراء العراقية
equipped with these five million dollar cameras
مدعمين بكميرات تصوير بقيمة 5 ملايين دولار
that allowed them to see the entire desert floor.
تمكنهم من رؤية كامل الصحراء العراقية
And their mission was to find and to destroy --
وكانت المهمة ايجاد وتدمير
remember the Scud missile launchers,
قاذفات صواريخ " سكود "
those surface-to-air missiles
الصواريخ الأرض جو
that the Iraqis were launching at the Israelis?
التي أطلقها العراقيون على أسرائيل - هل تذكرونها ؟
The mission of the two squadrons
كانت مهمة السربين
was to get rid of all the Scud missile launchers.
هي التخلص من تلك القاذفات - قاذفات صواريخ سكود -
And so they flew missions day and night,
فقام السربين بطلعات جوية طيلة الليل والنهار
and they dropped thousands of bombs,
والقوا آلاف القنابل
and they fired thousands of missiles
واطلقوا الآلاف من الصواريخ
in an attempt to get rid of this particular scourge.
في محاولة لضرب تلك المنظومة تحديداً
And after the war was over, there was an audit done --
وبعد انتهاء الحرب كان هناك تدقيق
as the army always does, the air force always does --
الجيش دوما يقوم بذلك .. وسلاح الجو يقوم بذلك دوماً
and they asked the question:
وكان السؤال المطروح حينها
how many Scuds did we actually destroy?
كم عدد صواريخ سكود التي تم تدميرها فعلاً ؟
You know what the answer was?
هل تعلمون ما هي الاجابة ؟
Zero, not a single one.
صفر ! لم يصيبوا أياً منها !
Now why is that?
لماذا هذا ؟
Is it because their weapons weren't accurate?
هل بسبب ضعف دقة الأسلحة ؟
Oh no, they were brilliantly accurate.
لا .. فقد كانت فائقة الدقة
They could have destroyed this little thing right here
فقد كانوا يستطيعون تدمير اصغر جزيء
from 25,000 ft.
من ارتفاع 25 ألف قدم
The issue was they didn't know where the Scud launchers were.
المشكلة هي أنهم لم يكونوا يعرفون أين هي قاذفات صواريخ سكود
The problem with bombs and pickle barrels
ان المشكلة فيما يخص القنابل و براميل المخلل !
is not getting the bomb inside the pickle barrel,
هي ليست القاء القنبلة داخل البرميل
it's knowing how to find the pickle barrel.
بل هي معرفة مكان البرميل
That's always been the harder problem
انها المشكلة الاكبر
when it comes to fighting wars.
في الحروب المستعرة
Or take the battle in Afghanistan.
أو لنأخذ المعركة في افغانستان
What is the signature weapon
ماهو السلاح الرمز في تلك الحرب
of the CIA's war in Northwest Pakistan?
الاستخباراتية الجارية في شمال غرب باكستان
It's the drone. What is the drone?
انه الطائرة بلا طيار" الدرون " ! اتعلمون ما هو الدرون !
Well it is the grandson of the Norden Mark 15 bombsight.
إنه حفيد موجه "نوردن " للقنابل
It is this weapon of devastating accuracy and precision.
انه السلاح الاكثر دقة و فاعلية
And over the course of the last six years
و في السنوات الستة الماضية
in Northwest Pakistan,
في شمال غرب باكستان
the CIA has flown hundreds of drone missiles,
قامت الاستخبارات المركزية بإطلاق مئات الصواريخ من نوع " درون "
and it's used those drones
وباستخدام الدرون
to kill 2,000 suspected
تم قتل ما يقارب 2000 مشتبه به
Pakistani and Taliban militants.
من الميليشيات الباكستانية و الطالبانية
Now what is the accuracy of those drones?
حسناً ما هي دقة تلك " الدرون " ؟
Well it's extraordinary.
في الحقيقة كانت مميزة جداً
We think we're now at 95 percent accuracy
نحن نعتقد ان دقتها جاوزت ال95%
when it comes to drone strikes.
فعندما يأتي الامر لهجمات ال " درون "
95 percent of the people we kill need to be killed, right?
فإن 95% من الاشخاص المستهدفون يقتلون ! أليس كذلك ؟
That is one of the most extraordinary records
فهذا سجل مميز جداً
in the history of modern warfare.
في عصر الحروب الحديثة
But do you know what the crucial thing is?
ولكن أتعلمون ما هو الحكم هنا ؟
In that exact same period
أنه و في ذات المرحلة التي
that we've been using these drones
كنا نستخدم فيها ال " درون "
with devastating accuracy,
بدقته الباهرة
the number of attacks, of suicide attacks and terrorist attacks,
فان عدد الهجمات الانتحارية الارهابية
against American forces in Afghanistan
ضد القوات الامريكية في أفغانستان
has increased tenfold.
ارتفعت عشرة أضعاف
As we have gotten more and more efficient
وكلما تقدمنا اكثر في دقة
in killing them,
قتل الاعداء
they have become angrier and angrier
كلما اصبحوا اكثر غضباً
and more and more motivated to kill us.
واكثر تحفيزاً لمهاجمتنا
I have not described to you a success story.
انا لم اسرد لكم قصة نجاح !
I've described to you
لقد وصفت لكم
the opposite of a success story.
قصة معاكسة تماما لمفهوم النجاح
And this is the problem
والمشكلة هي
with our infatuation with the things we make.
انه و بولهنا بالاشياء التي نخترع
We think the things we make can solve our problems,
نحن نظن انه بالامكان معالجة مشاكلنا
but our problems are much more complex than that.
ولكن مشاكلنا باتت اكثر تعقيداً
The issue isn't the accuracy of the bombs you have,
فالقضية لم تعد دقة القنابل التي تملك
it's how you use the bombs you have,
بل كيفية الاستخدام
and more importantly,
والاهم من كل ذلك
whether you ought to use bombs at all.
هو هل يجب من الاساس استخدام تلك القنابل ؟ وهل يحتم عليك ذلك !
There's a postscript
وهناك ملاحظة ملحقة
to the Norden story
بخصوص قصة نوردن
of Carl Norden and his fabulous bombsight.
وموجه القنابل الشهير الخاص به
And that is, on August 6, 1945,
انه وفي السادس من اغسطس من عام 1945
a B-29 bomber called the Enola Gay
اقلعت طائرة قاذفة من طراز بي - 29 تدعى انولاجاي
flew over Japan
فوق اليابان
and, using a Norden bombsight,
واستخدمت موجه "نوردن " للقنابل
dropped a very large thermonuclear device
لكي تقوم برمي قنبلة نووية
on the city of Hiroshima.
فوق مدينة هوريشميا
And as was typical with the Norden bombsight,
وطبعاً موجه "نوردن " للقنابل
the bomb actually missed its target by 800 ft.
وجه القنبلة بعيداً عن الهدف ب 800 قدم
But of course, it didn't matter.
طبعاً لم تكن قضية كبيرة
And that's the greatest irony of all
وهذه هي " سخرية " الامر
when it comes to the Norden bombsight.
عندما يأتي الامر لخصوص موجه نوردن للقنابل
the air force's 1.5 billion dollar bombsight
فموجه القنابل ذا قيمة مليار ونصف المليار دولار الخاص بسلاح الجو
was used to drop its three billion dollar bomb,
قام برمي قنبلة بقيمة 3 مليارات دولار
which didn't need a bombsight at all.
لم تكن تحتاج على الاطلاق موجه قنابل
Meanwhile, back in New York,
في تلك الاثناء في نيويورك
no one told Carl Norden
لم يخبر احد كارل نوردن
that his bombsight was used over Hiroshima.
ان موجه القنابل خاصته تم استخدامه لقصف هوريشيما
He was a committed Christian.
فهو مسيحي ملتزم
He thought he had designed something
وقد ظن انه اخترع شيئاً
that would reduce the toll of suffering in war.
سوف يقلل من فاتورة المعاناة في الحروب
It would have broken his heart.
وان علم بذلك .. سيفطر قلبه لا محالة
(Applause)
(تصفيق)